Hello everyone, welcome back
to English Pod, my name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine,
so today we've got
a great upper
intermediate level lesson for
our learners and we're
talking about what?
Health care.
Okay, this is a very
important topic because
it's been in the news
recently, especially
in the context of American politics, and so
I don't know if you've heard things about
this listeners, but the
health care is a very hot topic.
Exactly, so basically
what we're talking about
is health insurance,
whether it's private
health insurance or, you know, like a
standard national insurance program.
Exactly, and so your
country might have a private
option where you can
pay a private company
for insurance or public
option like England
or Australia, where
your country will actually
provide health care
for you at no extra cost.
Very good.
So it's an interesting
topic, why don't we
jump directly into the
dialogue and we'll be
back to explain a couple things.
It was alright, I ran
into Bill and we got to
talking for a while,
he's in a bit of a jam.
What?
What happened?
Well, his son had an accident,
Bill doesn't have health insurance.
This really got me
thinking, and I wondered if
we shouldn't look into a
couple of different HMOs.
Yeah, you're right, we aren't getting
any younger and our kids are getting older.
Exactly.
I searched on the web and found a couple
of HMOs with low co-pays and good coverage.
The deductibles are low too.
Sounds good.
Although, do you think
we can qualify for insurance?
Those insurance companies are
real pirates when it comes to money.
Well, we don't have any pre-existing
illnesses or conditions, so we should be fine.
I wish our company or country
provided us with health care.
Not in a million years.
Alright, we're back.
So a lot of interesting vocab here.
Why don't we take a look at it
real fast in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
Okay, Marco, this
first phrase or acronym
actually is three words
that go together, HMO,
and they're very, very common
when you're talking about health care.
Right.
So an HMO means health
maintenance organization.
Okay, and so this is
a part of the health
insurance topic or we're talking about a
company that will provide health insurance.
Right, so it's a company that
provides health insurance, basically.
And if you go up to
an HMO, some of the
information that you receive is, for
example, what your co-pay will be.
Okay, so sometimes
with a private option when
you pay a company to
give you health insurance,
you can get a lower rate if you
help pay for some of your care.
So for example, a co-pay on
a broken arm might be $20.
But you pay $20 that's your co-pay and your
health insurance company pays the rest.
And so sometimes co-pays
are really high for the really big.
And that's kind of a
bad deal because if you
hurt yourself, you
don't want to pay a lot.
Right.
But sometimes there's
no co-pay in which case
your company will pay
for all of the coverage.
Alright, so another very
similar word is a deductible.
Okay, so deductible is something that
is fixed and it's in your insurance policy.
That means in the
contract that you make with
the insurance company that
a deductible will be stated.
For example, my insurance plan,
I have maybe a $500 deductible.
That means that in any
situation I get hurt or
I get sick, I pay for
the first $500 of care
and then my insurance
company pays for the rest.
Right.
So if I have to have a
$1,000 surgery, I pay $500
and then my insurance
company pays the other $500.
Okay.
Very good.
And well, you have these
deductibles in everything
and that depends on
your coverage, right?
So coverage, how much the HMO covers you?
That's right.
And so you can find
this also in your contract
with your insurance company and coverage
will include or not include something.
So coverage, for example, in a health care
plan does not usually include your teeth.
That's a separate kind of insurance.
Right.
That will include emergency
evacuation from from
from a situation or
ambulances, for example.
And so coverage is what is
included in your insurance plan.
Okay.
Very good.
And our last word for
today is to qualify for.
All right.
So you might have heard this phrase before
in the context of sports or academics.
So he qualified for a scholarship or she
qualified for the varsity volleyball team.
But in this case, to qualify for is
to be able to use the eligible for.
So sometimes HMOs,
like in, for example, the
United States, will not
accept a person who
has maybe some health
problems already because
that would be too much of
a risk, right, for the company.
All right.
So you could qualify for a reduced rate
because you have a very good health history.
Okay.
So this is very interesting.
And we have a couple of other phrases
that are very related to this language.
So why don't we move
on now to fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
All right.
So in fluency builder today,
let's take a look at our first phrase.
We got to talking for a while.
Okay, we could say, for example, we started
talking or we were talking for a while.
But this is a very spoken language kind of
phrase where we'd say, we got to talking.
Right.
So it's not really
grammatically correct, but
because you would
say, we started talking.
But sometimes people
say, we got to talking.
So we got into a conversation, right?
That's right.
And usually it's about something.
So we could say, yeah,
we got to talking about
how we both went to
the same high school.
Or we got to talking about this movie
that we both saw, okay, very good.
And well, they got to talking for a while.
And apparently his
friend was in a bit of a jam.
Okay, jam is a food you can eat it.
You put it on bread, like marmalade, right?
Exactly.
But in this case, a jam is
a fix or a difficult situation.
So it has a very different meaning.
And I want to warn
you about that first, but
to be in a jam or to be in a
bit of a jam is to be stuck, okay?
So you're in a difficult situation.
You have some problem.
Yeah, so Marco, I'm in a bit of a jam here.
Can I get your help with something?
All right, very good.
Okay.
And then the guy was
talking about insurance
and he said, this
really got me thinking.
So we got the verb got again there.
All right.
So got me thinking.
That means I started
thinking about something.
So you know, when we were
talking about jam a minute
ago, it got me thinking about
how much I love breakfast.
Very good.
So you would use it in that way.
Like it reminded me.
It reminded me or I started to
really think about something, okay?
And our last phrase
is a pre-existing illness.
All right.
So to exist is to be,
you know, to be around
preexisting means existing
before something else.
Okay.
And so you often hear
this in terms of insurance
when someone asks you
about your preexisting condition.
So that means if I'm
signing up for an insurance
plan, health insurance
plan, and I have
an interview with you, Marco,
and you asked me this question.
What is your pre-existing condition?
That means what diseases
or health problems do I have
right now prior to signing
up for this insurance?
And I say, oh, I don't
have any and you're
very happy because
that means I'll be cheap.
But if I say, oh, I have
diabetes, then that
is something that the insurance companies
don't like because it's expensive.
Right.
Because you're more probable of
getting sick or something like that.
Right.
So diabetes or cancer or Lyme disease,
these are all preexisting conditions.
And usually, preexisting
conditions are diseases
or problems, health problems
that you have that won't go away.
Okay.
Very good.
All right.
So we have a lot of
words, a lot of phrases here.
Let's listen to the dialogue
one last time and we'll be back.
Hey, honey, how was your day?
It was all right.
I ran into Bill and we
got to talking for a while.
He's in a bit of a jam.
What?
What happened?
Well, his son had an accident,
Bill doesn't have health insurance.
This really got me
thinking and I wondered if
we shouldn't look into a
couple of different HMOs.
Yeah.
You're right.
We aren't getting any younger
and our kids are getting older.
Exactly.
I searched on the web and found a couple
of HMOs with low co-pays and good coverage.
The deductibles are low too.
Sounds good.
Although, do you think
we can qualify for insurance?
Those insurance companies are
real pirates when it comes to money.
Well, we don't have any
preexisting illnesses or conditions.
So we should be fine.
I wish our company or country
provided us with healthcare.
Not in a million years.
Right.
So the healthcare
issue is pretty heated
debate now in the United
States because many
people don't have healthcare
and it's not very accessible, right?
That's right.
And it's a huge debate because
it's very, very divided by party lines.
We say, you know,
there's the Republicans on
the right and there's
the Democrats on the
left and the Democrats want
a public healthcare option.
They want healthcare to be
available for everyone, for free.
And many of them do.
And a lot of Republicans
say no, it should be
private because if it's
private, there's competition
and that means there's
better healthcare.
And so there's a really big debate and
people are getting very angry about it.
Yeah.
But I think it's something
that's very interesting
and most importantly
seeing the difference
of healthcare systems
around the world, right?
So for example, our listeners,
they're from everywhere in the world.
So we would like to know, what
the healthcare system is like there.
Do you have free
universal healthcare in your
country or do you also have to pay for
private companies or private health insurance?
And if you have one or the other
system, do you think it's a good thing?
Do you think it's a bad thing?
What do you think needs some work?
Right.
I definitely agree with
universal healthcare.
I think it's a relief because it's
like one thing less to worry about.
I can't imagine like,
you know, if I don't
have healthcare right
now and I'm that covered
by a private company
and something happens
to me tomorrow, then, you
know, what's going to happen?
And I think it's a basic
human right, personally.
So I think it's in the
best interests of a
country to invest in it
because it means that
there people are more
productive and happier and healthy.
Yeah.
All right.
So that's all the time we have for today.
Be sure to come to EnglishPod.com,
leave your questions and comments.
And we'll see you guys there.
Bye, everyone.
Bye.